Part Three: Lidocaine.
If you are having trouble eating
and swallowing due to the mucositis,
often the next step is to add a numbing
rinse to numb your mouth and throat.
We use 2% viscous lidocaine
to rinse your mouth with.
Use 10 to 15ml to
rinse your mouth with.
If your areas of pain are deep
in the back of the throat
or in the neck or esophagus,
you can also swallow the lidocaine.
This will provide your mouth and or throat
a 15 minute
window of numbness, during
which you can eat and drink more easily.
You can use lidocaine before every meal.
If there are small areas of pain,
you can also use a Q-Tip
to dab lidocaine
in the specific area of mucositis
that is causing you discomfort
or preventing you from eating.
Please be sure that when using lidocaine
and eating that you sit
upright and swallow food carefully
so it goes down the esophagus.
We do not want you to aspirate
food or liquid.
Also,
be careful
when chewing
since your tongue will be numb.
You want to chew slowly and carefully
so you do not bite your tongue
or your gums accidentally.